Alright, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף daf is י״ג. Yud
Gimmel. We pick up at the bottom of י״ב עמוד ב׳. Yud
Beis Amud Beis. We're dealing with different things that are כשר kosher
or פסול pasul for סכך, schach, primarily with a look towards the
issue of מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. We discussed like different stages of
the making of flax into a string and now we pick up
with the following statement, two lines from the bottom of
י״ב עמוד ב׳. Yud Beis Amud Beis. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav
Yehuda says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, הני שושי ושובצירי, hani shushe v'shavtzire,
מסככין בהם, mesachchin bahem,
these two things, שושי shushe and שובצירי, shavtzire, which are various types
of vegetables,
you can use for, and you can, they have like wide leaves,
you can use them, or presumably not them because they're food, but
their leaves for סכך. schach. מסככין בהו. mesachchin behu.
Yeah, so fine. So they're, their leaves, right.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, בשושי מסככין בשובצירי לא מסככין.
beshushe mesachchin beshavtzire lo mesachchin. No, you can use this שושי, shushe,
you can't use this
שובצירי. shavtzire. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why not? שובצירי דצרי ריחייהו shavtzire
d'tzari reichaihu because once they spoil, they're, you know what, once it
starts withering, then it starts making a stink, the leaves,
ושביק להו ונפיק. v'shavik lehu v'nafik. Then you'll leave your סוכה sukkah
and you'll walk out. So for אביי, Abaye, and this is actually
something that we've seen, excuse me, something we've seen from אביי Abaye
in the past, is that אביי Abaye focuses us not just on
the technical question of is this a כשר kosher object, is this
the right size, but also the reality of have you created a
סוכה sukkah that's habitable. There was a case before about in which
you have לא סכך lo schach and you have like strands of
סכך schach hanging within י׳ טפחים, ten tefachim, that even though technically
that doesn't mean that the size of the סוכה sukkah is any
smaller, the reality is it makes it no longer habitable. So the
point here he's saying is the same thing. These leaves might be
כשר סכך, kosher schach, but you can't use it for a סוכה
sukkah because it'll spoil and you'll leave. Now, it's interesting, right, if
he's saying that rabbinically you're not יוצא, yotzei, is he saying לכתחילה
lechatchila you shouldn't? Why don't I say I'll use it until it
gets bad and then I'll leave or whatever? But it sounds like
אביי Abaye is doing more than just giving advice. אביי Abaye is
saying that since it's set up in a way that it's not
really habitable in any serious, under normal conditions or over a period
of time, it is not considered a דירה dirah and you're not
יוצא. yotzei. Similarly, we have the next debate. Again, top line of
י״ג עמוד א׳. Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph. אמר רב חנין בר רבא,
Amar Rav Hanin bar Rava, הני היזמי והיגי, hani hizmi v'higi, various
types of thorn bushes, מסככין בהו, mesachchin behu, you can use them
because again, you cut them off of the ground and it grows
from the ground, it's not מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, why not? אביי
אמר בהיזמי מסככין, Abaye amar behizmi mesachchin, היזמי hizmi which is one
type of a thorn bush you can use, היגי higi which is
a different type of a thorn bush, לא מסככין, lo mesachchin, you
can't use. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why not? כיון דנתרי טרפייהו שביק
לה ונפיק keivan d'natri tarfaihu shavik la v'nafik because the second type
of bush naturally the leaves will start, once cut off from the
ground and on top of your סכך schach maybe exposed to sun,
eventually the leaves will start dropping off of the bush and fall
down and therefore, not just that you'll be left with not sufficient
סכך, schach, but then it'll start becoming uninhabitable because you'll have all
these leaves falling onto your head and into your soup and onto
your food. So therefore, it's not good. Again, is that just לכתחילה,
lechatchila, is that even בדיעבד, bedieved, is he claiming that rabbinically, is
he claiming that biblically? But אביי Abaye does have a consistent position
that he says we're not just looking at the technical parameters, if
it's not really going to be habitable because of the circumstances, to
me that's a problem as well. Okay, now we get back to
the point of our משנה mishna which was a bundle of wood
you can't use and trying to more precisely define or deal with
cases of what constitutes a bundle. So let's take a look.
אמר רב גידל אמר רב Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav says רב
גידל Rav Gidel in the name of רב, Rav, האי אפקוסטא דדיקלא,
hai afkusta d'dikla, if you have a, I don't know how they
translate it, but basically the רש״י Rashi says it, it's like a,
it's like a bundle but it's a natural bundle, like a collection
of shoots of like palm branches, but all coming from a sort
of a common source. I'm trying to think of what a good
example would be, but maybe it's not, this is not what the
גמרא Gemara is talking about because the גמרא Gemara is talking about
a palm tree or things that grow at the base of a
palm tree. But if you think about, let's say I were to
chop off a branch of a tree, right, would I say well
that's like a bundle of wood because it's got one branch and
I've got all these sticks of wood coming from it? And the
answer is no, because that's a natural bundle, it's not a man-made
bundle. So this is the same type of an idea, like a
lot of shoots. You know what's a good example would be? Again,
this wouldn't be directly relevant because this is food, so it wouldn't
be כשר kosher anyway, but think about like a
bunch of celery, right, where you've got all these stalks, right, which
are bunched at the bottom. So it almost looks like a bundle
of wood, right, it's like a lot of stalks of things, but
they're all naturally joined at the bottom. So he's saying that's not
a problem, again, we're not dealing with food, okay, so then it
would be מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, that's not a problem because that's
a bundle but it's not a human-made bundle, a man-made bundle. Okay,
so מסככינן. Mesachchinan. אף על גב דאגידי, Af al gav de'agidi, although
they are bundled up,
אגד בידי שמים לא שמיה אגד. Eged bidei Shamayim lo shmei eged.
It's made by heaven as it were, the knot. You know, they're
joined together naturally, they're not humanly bound.
Now, אמר רב חסדא אמר רבינא בר שילא, Amar Rav Chisda amar
Ravina bar Shila, as if to explain. No, אמר רב חסדא אמר
רבינא בר שילא. Amar Rav Chisda amar Ravina bar Shila. Now you
went ahead again, think about the bunch of celery is the best
like visual example, although again we're not talking about food. Now you
went ahead, it had that natural joining at the bottom, and you
took a string and you made a string around the stalks, you
know, at the top, so you actually made a human bundle. Even
though you did that, even though
you "everything was still joined",
"yeah, it started joined naturally, and now you're going to put a
string around it and join it together",
"instead of taking it tearing it apart and putting it back",
"right, if you tore it apart it'd be different", but no, it
was already naturally joined. אגדי להו. Agdei lehu.
אגד בחד לא שמיה אגד. Eged bechad lo shmei eged. Joining something
that's already one is not an אגד. eged. You've already decided that
since it's natural, it's considered to basically be one unit. It's not
considered to be multiple units joined together. So therefore, if you now
made a string around your celery stalks, you haven't bundled up celery
stalks because it was already one unit. So even if you added
a string to it, you would not have made it into a
bundle, you would not have made it a problem. אמר רב חסדא
אמר רבינא בר שילא, Amar Rav Chisda amar Ravina bar Shila, הני
דוקרי דקני. hani dukrei de'kanei. This is basically the same thing except
instead of talking about some type of stalks or whatever that grow
by from a palm, this is talking about the same type of
things with reeds. That you have like a collection of a shoot
of reeds all coming out that are joined at the bottom. מסככינן
בהו, Mesachchinan behu, you can use that for סכך. s'chach. אף על
גב דאגידי, Af al gav de'agidi, although they're naturally joined together, אגד
בידי שמים לא שמיה אגד. Eged bidei Shamayim lo shmei eged. It's
all done naturally and therefore it's not considered like a bundle. Adding
nothing, just applying it to a case of reeds. If you knew
the difference between the, if you, you know, if you had experience
with the palm branches and with the reeds, you might appreciate what
the חידוש chiddush is, but I have no idea. It's the same
idea except this is with reeds. אף על גב דהדר אגדי להו,
Af al gav de'hadar agdei lehu, even though you then went ahead
and now you made a bundle around, like a loop, a knot
around these reeds, אגד בחד לא שמיה אגד. Eged bechad lo shmei
eged. Joining something, bundling something that's already one unit is not making
an אגד eged and therefore even if you made a bundle on
it, as long as they remain naturally connected at the bottom, it
is not a problem. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, similarly, קנים
ודוקרנים, kanim ve'dukranim,
reeds or sticks literally and דוקרנים, dukranim, which is דוקרנים dukranim is
also like some type of a poles. מסככינן בהן. Mesachchinan bahen. You
can make it with סכך. s'chach. The גמרא Gemara says, קנים, kanim,
פשיטא. pishita. So reeds is like obvious. So why couldn't you make
it? It didn't say it's a bundle, it just said reeds. Of
course you can make סכך s'chach with reeds. אימא קנים של דוקרנין
מסככינן בהן. Eima kanim shel dukranin mesachchinan bahen. No, so what it
means is reeds that are of דוקרנין dukranin and here again whatever
this means is the reeds that are of this type of a
bunch. So it's not referring to two things, it's referring to one
thing. A bunch of reeds, a naturally growing bunch of reeds you
can use it for סכך. s'chach. And that's the idea we said,
that although they're bunched together, since it's natural, it is not considered
to be a bundle and it's okay. Okay. ואמר רב חסדא אמר
רבינא בר שילא, Ve'amar Rav Chisda amar Ravina bar Shila, הני מרואתא
דאגמא, hani maruata de'agma,
if you have bitter herbs of the swamp, אדם יוצא בהן ידי
חובתו בפסח. adam yotzei bahen yedei chovato be'Pesach. You can use it
to fulfill your obligation on פסח. Pesach. It counts as מרור. maror.
And the חידוש chiddush is going to be, although it has a
what's called a שם לווי, shem livai, a qualifying name, a descriptive
name. It's not just called generically מרור. maror. It's called swamp מרור.
maror. Nevertheless, that's in the category of מרור. maror. The additional characterizing
name, qualifying name,
descriptive name does not make it a different subspecies, doesn't make it
a different type of a plant. Now, the only reason now we're
saying it is because it's אמר רב חסדא אמר רבינא. amar Rav
Chisda amar Ravina. It has nothing to do with סכך. s'chach. If
you look before, the statement about דוקרי דקני dukrei de'kanei was אמר
רב חסדא אמר רבינא. amar Rav Chisda amar Ravina. So this is
really completely unrelated, it's just the same person who says it. Okay.
So the same source of tradition, Rav Chisda in the name of
Ravina, is a הלכה halacha about הלכות פסח. hilchos Pesach. You can
use horseradish, that's swamp horseradish. Now I think by the way the
etymology, I forgot to check this, the etymology of the word horseradish
has something to do with swamp, like horse is not a horse,
it's from
let me see if I can find it right now. Somehow it's
through some poor translation, some type of a translation that ultimately is
rooted in something I think like a radish of the sea or
a radish of the swamp. Hold on a second, use Rabbi Google
here.
Let's see what Wikipedia has to say. What? Excellent rabbi, Rabbi Google,
he always knows everything. You know, the thing is, he's never available
on שבת. Shabbos.
Okay,
let's take a look.
Let's see if it says anything about the
etymology.
No,
horse meaning strong, strong radish. Okay, I thought it was something else,
that actually that the word came somehow from something relating to sea
radish or swamp radish. Horse is a strong animal. Anyway, fine. Okay,
so anyway, all right. So he says that radish, this, this horse
radish of the bitter herbs of the swamp you can use. Now,
what's the חידוש? chiddush? So it says like this. מיתיבי, Meitivi, I'll
ask you on this. The
חידוש chiddush is that it has this qualifying name of the swamps.
אזוב, Eizov, when the Torah says you have to use a bunch
of hyssop for the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, and then we also
link it to using a bunch of hyssop for like the sprinkling
of the ashes of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it says אגודת
אזוב, Agudas Eizov, a bunch of hyssop. So אזוב Eizov ולא, velo,
oh, actually later we're going to deal with the idea that it
says a bunch, right? And what constitutes a bunch when we say
a bunch of hyssop, the same way here we say an אגודה,
agudah, a bunch of sticks. But here the focus is just going
to be on what plant constitutes hyssop.
אזוב Eizov ולא אזוב יוון, velo Eizov Yavan, not Greek hyssop, ולא
אזוב כוחלי, velo Eizov Koachli, and not bluish אזוב, Eizov, ולא אזוב
מדברי velo Eizov Midbari or wilderness hyssop, ולא אזוב רומי velo Eizov
Romi or Roman hyssop, ולא אזוב שיש לו שם לווי, velo Eizov
sheyesh lo shem livai, not any type of a hyssop that has
a
qualifying attendant name, some type of a descriptive name. That makes it
a sub-species and not standard אזוב. Eizov. So if that's true, why
not say the same about horse radish? It has to be called
מרור maror and not מרור maror of the swamp. So אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, כל שנשתנה שמו קודם מתן תורה. kol shenishtanah shemo kodem
Mattan Torah. No, here's the difference. If it did have a different
name, meaning did it have a, you know, a, a
qualifying name, it wasn't generic, it was some type of a, you
know, x-type of horse radish, x-אזוב, Eizov, Greek hyssop, Roman hyssop. Did
it have that qualifier name, that attendant name? If it had that
before the Torah was given, ובאה התורה והקפידה עליה, uva haTorah vehikpida
aleha, and then the Torah came along and did not say any
word that would suggest something more inclusive, it just used the standard
generic term hyssop, and so if there were other types of hyssop,
Greek hyssop, Roman hyssop, this and that, and the Torah just said
hyssop, so we're saying only standard hyssop, not any of these sub-species.
So בידוע, beyadua,
meaning it was mentioned twice in the Torah?
Yes. No, no, no. נשתנה nishtanah is a slightly misleading term. It
just means it has a, that it has a different name. It's
not just included in the broad generic name hyssop. Before the Torah
was given there already was a species known as Roman hyssop and
as Greek hyssop and as blue hyssop. There were other types of
hyssop out there. And the Torah came and said hyssop without indicating
hyssops in the plural, without in any way a suggesting the idea
that it was an inclusive word. So that means just the standard,
not these, not these variations.
So that's a bit of a, I guess, from, since
they didn't really have the science, you know,
how do you know what they had at the time of מתן
תורה? Mattan Torah? Yeah, that is a good question. Okay. ובאה התורה
והקפידה עליה. uva haTorah vehikpida aleha. The Torah came and was מקפיד,
makpid, meaning of only somehow by silence it was מקפיד makpid to
say only the standard variation. בידוע שיש לו שם לווי. beyadua sheyesh
lo shem livai. So therefore it is
known that it has an attendant name. Meaning that the presence of
the attendant name makes it a different species and not acceptable. It's
a funny way of saying it, but that seems to be the
point. והני, ve'hani, these, the other types of horse radish, לא נשתנה
שמייהו קודם מתן תורה כלל. lo nishtanah shemaihu kodem Mattan Torah klal.
They didn't have, they weren't known as a sub-species at the time
of, at the time the Torah was given. So the מרור maror
of the Torah includes them. They only got some sub-categorization later. So
they were never excluded by the word מרור maror of the Torah.
So one answer is a fascinating, right, historical answer which is like
exactly this question, how did they know when these names differed and
so on. Okay. רבא אמר, Rava amar, has another answer. הני מרירתא
סתמא שמייהו. hani merirata stama shemaihu. No, no, no. These things that
you call swamp מרור maror are really just called מרור. maror. והאי
דקרי להו מרירתא דאגמא, ve'hai dekari lehu merirata de'agma, the fact that
they're called swamp מרור, maror, משום דמשתכח באגמא, mishum demishtachach be'agma,
they're found in the swamp. Meaning it's not a proper name, it's
a descriptive name. Right? If I said to you go get me
some, what would be the example, I don't know,
red peppers and orange peppers and green peppers, right? I don't know,
maybe those are different species, but I'm just, you know, using it
to describe what color I want, I'm not using it as a
different type of a species of a pepper. And the green one's
an unripe pepper; it's a different color. Really? Okay, even a better,
even a better גמרא! Gemara! So swamp מרור maror means, yeah, the
type that grows in the swamp, but we're not saying that in
some official scientific way it's a subspecies, which is also fascinating because,
you know, they didn't have like a science of taxonomy of, I
don't think they did, you know, of vegetables at the time. So
what would put something in a separate subspecies? Meaning, you know, would
it, presumably it would just be how people would use it, like
the, you know, the way in which people would refer to it.
So he's still maybe saying that even from the way people refer
to it, they don't identify it, they don't call it like swamp
מרור maror with capital S and capital M. They call it lowercase
S. You know, people still, even when they, even if we're not
going by science, even if we're going by human categorization, they're still
using that identifier as a, you know, as an, as an, as
an adjective and not as a proper noun and therefore it's not
really a different species. Anyway, I would have said two things I
would say. First is that I would have said, and this is
a point the גמרא Gemara makes in פסחים, Pesachim,
you know, there's a better answer, it would seem that there's a
better answer, which is the תורה Torah says מרורים, merorim, bitter herbs,
which is what allows the גמרא Gemara to say that you can
have multiple different types of things that constitute מרור, maror, you know,
even very different things, right? You can have horseradish, perhaps, possibly, there's
a debate whether horseradish still counts as מרור, maror, and you could
have like romaine lettuce, you know? It's not talking about one narrowly
defined species; it's bitter herbs in the plural, so it's a very
inclusive category. So that's true. My God, if you could go from
romaine lettuce to horseradish, so different types of horseradish presumably would be
included as well. It's the תורה's Torah's word is more of a
descriptive word than a, you know, than a sort of a species
term, than a proper term. So it's funny that the גמרא Gemara
doesn't suggest that to allow it to be more descriptive either. Anyway,
this idea of the גמרא Gemara about שם לוואי shem livai and
is it the thing itself or not, you know, it comes up
a number of times in the גמרא. Gemara. I remember it was
just like a month ago, it was such a funny bit I
saw on Jon Stewart, on the Daily Show, where he did something
which was like a perfect illustration of this. He was like ranking
on Chicago, you know, and Chicago has like, you know, what is
it, deep dish pizza? So he was going on and on about
how like, you know, about how they talk about how their, you
know, pizza is whatever so amazing and it was, anyways, he's ranking
on it as, you know, that it doesn't, you know, about how
it's not doesn't really taste as good as New York pizza. Anyway,
the last part he did was,
and you know what Chicago, he says, you know what you call
this? You call this deep dish pizza, Chicago pizza, he says, you
know what this is? And he picks up a slice of pizza.
Pizza. So you know,
שם לוואי, shem livai, it's not the real thing.
All right, anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב חסדא, Amar
Rav Chisda, says
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
אגד בחד לאו שמיה אגד. eged bechad lo shemei eged. We just
said that if you bind one thing up and it's already one
unit, like these different stalks that are combined at the bottom, it's
not considered a bundle. You don't make a bundle with one unit
even if it's somehow different stalks combined in a unit.
אגד שלוש שמיה אגד. eged shalosh shemei eged. However, if you have,
what is the minimum size of a bundle? As I mentioned to
you yesterday, that תוספות Tosafot quotes a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says twenty-five,
right? He is doing a much more minimalist approach. He is saying,
or a מחמיר machmir approach, that even three sticks bound together is
an אגד eged and you can't use it. שניים, shenayim, now what
if you have two stalks bound together? That's מחלוקת רבי יוסי ורבנן,
machloket Rabbi Yossi veRabbanan, a debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi and
the רבנן, Rabbanan, not by סוכה Sukkah but by another הלכה halacha
that there's an idea of אגד, eged, of a bundle, okay, which
is what and presumably he's saying that the same debate there would
apply to סוכה. Sukkah. What do we find there? דתנן, detnan, we
taught in the משנה, Mishna, מצות אזוב. mitzvat ezov. So now we're
talking about not just the
quality of the, the
thing that's the אזוב, ezov, what counts as hyssop, but the idea
that the תורה Torah says אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, a bundle of
hyssop. Now it says the bundle by the blood of the קרבן
פסח
Korban Pesach
in מצרים, Mitzrayim, but we also learned to apply this idea of
a bundle of אזוב ezov to like the sprinkling of the ashes
of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah that it has to be a
bundle. So how many make a bundle? So מצות אזוב, mitzvat ezov,
the מצוה mitzvah of the hyssop is בשלושה קלחים, bishloshah kelachim, three
stalks. ובהן שלושה גבעולים, uvehen sheloshah givolim, on them they have three,
like, heads, you know, whatever you call a head of ears. Okay,
now תוספות Tosafot says, רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say, it
doesn't mean three ears per stalk; it means one ear per stalk.
Okay, but they have to have their ears there as well. רבי
יוסי אומר מצות אזוב שלושה גבעולים. Rabbi Yossi omer mitzvat ezov sheloshah
givolim. No, the מצוה mitzvah of an אזוב ezov does start with
the idea of three stalks. ושיריו שניים. veshirav shenayim. But if after
you had the bundle and you bundled them all together and made
a knot around them, you know, one of them broke off and
you're left with two, two is okay as to retain that identity.
It has to start with three, but it could be left with
two. וגרדומו, vegardumo, and Let's say you have some remnant, it's that
you have a little piece of stalk left, most of it broke
off, but you have a little remnant left, כל שהוא, kol shehu,
even the smallest amount. This idea by the way is a common
one in הלכה Halakha that once something gets an identity, it has
a higher criteria to be labeled as something, but once it's labeled
as it, it retains that identity even even when a lot less
is left over. So for example, a common example I use is
for something to be considered food to be susceptible to become טמא,
tamei, it has to be first fit for human consumption. But once
it is labeled as food, and maybe also particularly once it becomes
טמא, tamei, then it does not stop being considered food until it
becomes not just unfit for human consumption, but even unfit for animal
consumption. That once it gets the label, it's much more resistant to
losing the label.
So you know you might have like a very high threshold before
hiring somebody for a job, but once they get the job, they're
going to have to really mess up before they get fired, okay,
like there's this idea of like of you know of of like
what I call the stickiness factor, okay, or the what is it,
the inertia factor, not exactly the same, but anyway. So that's the
idea here. You have the idea also maybe relevant similar to the
idea of the hyssop of a stringy type of a thing, the
גמרא Gemara in מנחות Menachot does this discussion about ציצית. tzitzit. Like
what you need for a string of ציצית tzitzit how long it
has to be to be כשר kosher when you make the ציצית,
tzitzit, but if after you made the ציצית tzitzit it snapped and
you're only left with a tiny little bit, so בדיעבד b'diavad what
you're left with is okay. So that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says, you have to start with three, but בדיעבד b'diavad after you
start with three, you can be left with two. And even of
those two presumably even if they break, as long as a little
bit is left, you're also okay. All right, so now this is
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it.
It says like this, וגרדומו v'gardumov is referring to the שניים shenayim
or the שלשה? shlosha?
Presumably the שניים. shenayim. קא סלקא דעתך מדשיריו שניים, ka salka daitach
mi'd'shiyarav shenayim, so we, I just gave you what the גמרא's Gemara
going to say at the end by רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, that's
the פשט pshat of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. But the גמרא Gemara
starts with a different assumption. We're assuming that since in the end
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says two, if you're left with two you're
okay, תחילתו נמי שניים, tchilato nami shenayim, he really would say you
could start with two. והאי דתני שלשה, v'hai d'tani shlosha, why does
he say you start with three? So למצוה, l'mitzvah, it means that
that's לכתחילה. l'chatchila. But since בדיעבד b'diavad since he's okay when you're
left with two, presumably even if you're starting with two it'd be
okay, three is just a nice לכתחילה. l'chatchila. מרבי
יוסי שלשה למצוה ורבנן שלשה לעכב. mi'Rabbi Yose shlosha l'mitzvah v'rabanan shlosha
l'akev. So for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose three is like a מצוה
mitzvah it's a לכתחילה, l'chatchila, but for the רבנן, Rabanan, so what's
their debate with the רבנן? Rabanan? Presumably the רבנן Rabanan say three,
they mean you need three even בדיעבד. b'diavad. So we try to
frame this debate of the רבנן Rabanan who say three and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose who says start with three and end with two
as a debate whether you need three or two. And therefore, that
seems to be a debate, when the תורה Torah said a bunch
of אזוב, ezov, אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, what's the minimum size for
a bunch? The רבנן Rabanan would say three, and רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose would say two, and that would be the debate. The גמרא
Gemara says, but you can't say that, והתניא v'hatanya we learned in
the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי יוסי אומר אזוב תחילתו שניים ושיריו אחד פסול.
Rabbi Yose omer ezov tchilato shenayim u'shiyarav echad pasul. Like in אזוב
ezov if you began with two and were left with one, maybe
it means even if you were left with one, or were left
with one, it's invalid. You cannot begin with two for your bunch
of אזוב. ezov. ואינו כשר v'eino kosher it's only כשר kosher עד
שתחילתו שלשה ad she'tchilato shlosha you must begin with three, then ושיריו
שניים u'shiyarav shenayim then if you're left with two that's fine, but
you must begin with three. So it's clear for רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose you have to begin with three, it's not just a nice
מצוה mitzvah and לכתחילה. l'chatchila. The גמרא Gemara says fine, איפכא, ifcha,
so reverse what we were saying. לרבי יוסי שלשה לעכב l'Rabbi Yose
shlosha l'akev for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose you see if you start
with less than three it's not good, you need three to you
know and less than three
it prevents you from being יוצא. yotzei. ולרבנן שלשה למצוה u'l'rabanan shlosha
l'mitzvah so when the רבנן Rabanan say three they're being actually more
lenient, they're saying it's a מצוה mitzvah to do three, whereas רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying no, you absolutely need to start with
three. You don't need to end with three, but you need to
start it. Okay, and how is this relevant to us? So we've
now interpreted the debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and the רבנן
Rabanan by the bunch of hyssop for like the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach and for the what do you call it, for the פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says you must start
with three and the רבנן Rabanan say three is לכתחילה l'chatchila but
בדיעבד b'diavad it's okay to start with two. So that's a debate
what is the minimum number of things that constitutes a bunch? For
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose it's three, for the רבנן Rabanan it's two.
Just show you a fascinating little תוספות, Tosafot, because you'll like the
תוספות Tosafot where he's bringing his proof. בשלשה שמי אגד. bi'shlosha shemi
aged. תוספות Tosafot says תימה, teima, דבמסכת אבות משמע d'v'Masechet Avot mashma
that in מסכת אבות Masechet Avot it
implies דפחות מחמשה לא שמי אגד. d'pachot mi'chamisha lo shemi aged.
דתנן, d'tnan, עשרה שיושבין ועוסקין בתורה שכינה ביניהם asarah she'yoshvin v'oskin ba'Torah
Shechinah beineihem
ten people who are learning תורה Torah the שכינה Shechinah is amongst
them, שנאמר אלקים נצב בעדת ק-ל, she'ne'emar Elokim nitzav ba'adat E-l,
that's an עדה. edah. ומניין אפילו חמשה u'minayin afilu chamisha how do
you know even five people? שנאמר ואגודתו על ארץ יסדה, she'ne'emar va'agudato
al eretz yesadah,
the bunch is on is established on the land, so you see
a bunch is five people. Okay, so not three. ומניין אפילו שלשה
u'minayin afilu shlosha how do you know even three? שנאמר... she'ne'emar... Remember
be careful ישפט. yishpot. Okay, so that's what we said.
Yeah, the משנה Mishnah in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot says ten people
learning תורה Torah God is among them 'cause it says God is
among the congregation and a congregation is ten. How do you know
even five people? 'Cause it says, "God's bunch is established on the
earth," so אגודה agudah is five. And how do you know even
I don't know, but it assumes that אגודה agudah is five. אגודה's
agudah a bunch. Oh okay. And how do you know that's what
we're talking about? אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, an אגד, eged, right? So
for the bunch of hyssop or for the סכך. schach. And how
do you know even three? 'Cause it says, you know, 'cause it
says what's the פסוק pasuk for three?
בקרב אלהים ישפט, bekerev elohim yishpot, in the midst. So midst means
how many people you have to have a midst of them? A
middle, you need an odd number, you need three. So it says
it looks like אגודה's agudah five, not אגודה's agudah three. So he
says ואיכא דגרסי איפכא חמשה נפקא לן מן בקרב, ve'ika degarsi ipcha
chamisha nafka lan min bekerev,
so he says some reversed the גרסא girsa that בקרב אלהים ישפט
bekerev elohim yishpot is five and אגודה agudah is three to make
it reconcile with this גמרא, Gemara, but תוספות Tosafot says it doesn't
really make so much sense. So in the end תוספות Tosafot says
maybe, if you look, you want to look at how he answers
it, three lines from the end of that תוספות, Tosafot, he says
ושמא דאף על גב דאמרינן חשיבא אגודה בשלשה, veshema de'af al gav
de'amrinan chashiva agudah bishlosha,
maybe in normal אגודה agudah is three like we say here and
that's what you need for אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, three strands, three
stalks of hyssop. האי קרא דואגודתו על ארץ יסדה לא מיתוקם אלא
בחמשה, hai kra deva'agudato al eretz yisadah lo mitokam ela bechamisha, the
verse of God's group is established on the land means five. Why?
משום דכתיב mishum dechtiv because the verse that's next to it says
אף ידי יסדה ארץ, af yadi yisadah eretz, My hand has
shaped the land, וביד יש בה חמשה אצבעות, ubeyad yesh bah chamisha
etzba'ot, and a hand has five, so the group means the bunch
of fingers. All right, anyway it's key that he's trying to make
a like learn out from the משנה Mishnah in פרקי אבות, Pirkei
Avot, right, which also focused on the word אגודה agudah and what
is the minimum of אגודה. agudah.
The גמרא Gemara does that, right? Like quotes from אבות Avot to
prove something else?
It does quote from אבות. Avot.
Yeah, do something like I
think yeah I don't remember offhand but I know it's there definitely.
Okay, anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. ועתה, ve'ata, now. So now we've got this debate whether three
or two hyssops, which we're saying also would translate into the issue
of סכך. schach. והתניא, vehatanya, don't we teach in a ברייתא: braita:
איזו תחילתו שנים ושיורו אחד כשר, eizo techilato shnayim veshiuro echad kasher,
an אזוב ezov that
has to begin with two and if it ends with one it's
כשר. kasher. No, והתניא vehatanya actually is not a challenge, it's a
support, so this is going to show that the rabbis, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi says you need to start with three, the rabbis are
going to say that you can start with two by אזוב ezov
because the ברייתא braita says if you start with two and you're
left with one it's okay. ואינו פסול עד שתחילתו ושיורו אחד, ve'eino
pasul ad shetechilato veshiuro echad, it's only invalid if you start with
one and end with one. So you see it can't be רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says you have to start
with three. So this must be the rabbis and it says you
can start with two. So we see there is that debate between
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and the rabbis that minimally you can start
with three or two. What is the minimum size of an אגודה?
agudah? Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says שיורו אחד פסול הא תניא
שיורו אחד כשר. shiuro echad pasul ha tanya shiuro echad kasher. What
does it mean that it's invalid if you're left with one? We
said it's valid if you're left with one as long as you
begin with two. חסורי מחסרא, chasuri mechasra, that's what it means. It
means אלא אימא, ela eima, you can read it: עד שתחילתו כשיורו
אחד. ad shetechilato keshiuro echad. It's invalid if you start with what
normally we let you end with. If you start with one, that's
invalid. If you started with two, it's okay to end with one,
but you need to start with two, as opposed to רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi that says you need to start with three and end
with two. The rabbis say you need to start with two. If
you start with two you can end with one. Yeah. But anyway,
we have basically said that when it comes to אזוב, ezov, an
אגודה agudah is three or two, so presumably for the משנה Mishnah
although obviously it could have been a very different definition—the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
thinks it's a radically different definition, it's twenty-five, 'cause the purpose of
our משנה Mishnah is not just a, you know, some abstract, you
know, Platonic idea of what is a minimum size of a bunch,
three makes a bunch. It's a practical issue that you're going to,
you know, come with your bundle of wood and put it on
top of your סכך, schach, so they limit it to normal cases
of a normal size of a bundle of wood, they limit it
to twenty-five. Our גמרא Gemara makes it much more formalistic definition of
bundle and says even three, presumably the same definition for אזוב ezov
that would be the issue for how many minimum stalks or minimum
pieces of wood would be invalid to use for the סכך. schach.
Yeah.
So we have the מחלוקת machloket of לולב lulav versus אגד eged
or not, just the same...
Yeah, that's a good point, that why don't we say that the
אגד eged there... Yeah, but although there it's not
a... Good point, I mean there you do have three things in
your אגד, eged, you know? So you have more than three if
you count the multiple pieces of the ערבה aravah and of the
whatever, so it's two, but there we're not saying a פסוק pasuk
starts with the word אגד. eged. The פסוק pasuk just uses ו
vav to combine them. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
דרש מרימר darsh Maremar back to trying to explore the parameters of
this idea of a bundle of wood. הני איסרי יסדא דסורא, hanni
isarei yasda desura, this bundle
of stalks from סורא, Sura, okay, מסככין בהו, mesach'chin behu, you could
use it. Now, why? What's special about it? אף על גב דאגדן,
Af al gav de-agdan, even though you made a bundle of them,
you knotted them together, למניינא בעלמא הוא דאגדן, Le-minyana be-alma hu de-agdan,
you're only doing it for number, meaning, you buy like you buy
something in the store and it's bundled together in order to give
you like a count of it. I'm trying to think what a
good example would be...
eggs in a box?
I guess like a dozen eggs in a box although this is
bundled with a string. Types of things that they would like—dozen roses.
A dozen roses.
Oh, that may be the nice example, right, a dozen roses. So
you don't really have the bundle as a way of carrying them,
right? It's done in order to know, well, you know, although you
know, right, it's—well, I don't know, because when you buy a dozen
roses, they might count a dozen and then they'll put the bundle.
It's not—like broccoli? You know they put a—they put a like
a string, you know, a thing... Oh, that's a good idea, like
a rubber band around the broccoli because they know you're buying x
number. You're buying them in units. So they're doing it in order
to give you a count and to make it easier to sell
them as a count, but not that the bundle is meant as
a means of actually, you know, for the purpose that they need
to be held together or for the means of conveying them or
carrying them. So it's not a normal bundle. It's a bundle just
for convenience of grouping them together for count, and therefore, even though
physically they're held together, that's not an official bundle and therefore it's
not a problem to use it for a סוכה, Sukkah, which is
a fascinating idea.
Fascinating because the whole reason we didn't want to use bundles in
the first place was because of גזירה. Gezeirah. It's not really anything
wrong with it, right?
It was a גזירה... Gezeirah... Actually, putting it on the top of
the סוכה Sukkah and when it's not made for סכך. Sechach. But
the point is that that's the point, that that idea that you'll
be carrying big bundles of things and put them on top of
the סוכה, Sukkah, so we're going to limit it to scenarios where
you really bundle things together. This is not really bundled together, right?
Okay,
so
למניינא בעלמא הוא דאגדן, Le-minyana be-alma hu de-agdan, they're only sort of
bundled for their number. אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, הני צריפי
דאורבני, Hanei tzrifay de-orbanei,
these types of like
huts for for trappers, so
that are כיון שהותרו ראשי מעדניהם כשרין. Keivan she-hutru rashei madaneihem keshayrin.
Once the top is undone, they're kosher. So basically, the way this
was made, it was sort of
like—yeah, right, so let's draw a picture here. It was sort of
like a teepee. You've got these like—רשי Rashi says these like basket
leaves,
these big willow branches, okay? And you sort of put them together,
right? You do it like that, and you make a knot at
the top, okay? And you've got at the bottom, like sort of
like, you know, it's sort of—it's conical, right? Not comical. Conical. Right?
Anyway, you know, you sort
of—it looks like this if you like turned it 90 degrees. So
you stick under here, it's sort of like, you know, it's sort
of like, you know, what do they call—like, you know, you're with
your rifle. It's like, I don't know. It's like you're going—what do
they call those, a blind? Like you're going hunting or whatever. So
you hide under there, okay? But this is what it looks like.
At the top, it's all these strands that are sort of not,
you know, these leaves or whatever that are bundled together, and at
the bottom, this part is sort of like woven together with like
some type of of a weave. It's not like bunched together, but
you know, it's sort of like there's like a weave that sort
of keeps it all together, keeps the cone together at the bottom
and at the top.
Like the mats. Like the mats.
Well, this goes back to the question Michael was asking on Shabbos
about the mats. So that's the bottom. But the top is more
of a normal bunching of them, right? So let's see what happens.
He says, כיון דשרי... Keivan desharei...
where are we? כיון שהותרו ראשי מעדניהם, Keivan she-hutru rashei madaneihem, once
you undo the head of their like of the leaves, the head
of the stalks, so כשרין, Keshayrin, it's kosher. So you can use
it now, it's no longer bundled together. I'm not sure it means
the—רשי Rashi says התקשרו במעדנות כימא... Hitkashru be-maadenot kima... I don't know,
like the stalks or the components of it. I don't know how
they translate it there in the English.
Usually it happens to say knots.
The knots, okay. The head of the knots.
The word for קשרים.
Kesharim. Yeah. Anyway, alright. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא אגידי מתתאי,
Ve-ha agidi mi-tataei,
and this is like, you know, Michael's question yesterday, but what about
the bottom? You know, the bottom it's all sort of woven together.
Now, that's not a bundle, right, because it's sort of keeping this
in this conical thing and it's like a weave of them together.
It's not like a big outer thing, right? This is Michael's question,
why isn't the mat a bundle? So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. Isn't it woven at the bottom? So אמר רב פפא
דשרי להו, Amar Rav Pappa desharei lehu, you undo it. Fine, you
undo the weave at the bottom, which then is a big—huge question.
So what's the חידוש Chiddush of the whole thing then? So רב
הונא בריה דרב יהודה אמר, Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehuda amar, ואיתימא,
V'itaima, ואמרי לה, V'amri lah, ואפילו תימא לא שרי, V'afeilu teima lo
sharei, ואיתימא, V'itaima, ואפילו תימא לא שרי, V'afeilu teima lo sharei, no
you don't undo the weave at the bottom. כל אגד שאינו עשוי
לטלטלו לא שמיה אגד. Kol eged she-eino asui le-taltelo lo shemei eged.
Okay, similar to the idea before that you're doing it for a
number, but he's basically saying that's done as a weave to hold
a shape, that's to create a shape. That's not done as a
way of bunching together discrete units and holding them so they're more
easier to carry. It's not a classic bundle. Which is sort of
what I said to Michael yesterday, a bundle is you have discrete
units and you're putting some outer thing around it, and the גמרא
Gemara specifically identifies like even that the purpose matters. Are you doing
it just for the number, you know, to sell it as a
unit, or are you doing it actually to convey it? This is
not—is a different physical reality. It's not like an outer thing bundling
things together, it's done to give it a particular shape. Now רשי
Rashi by the way does
say... To look at רש"י *Rashi*, שאינו עשוי למטלטלו *she-eino asui le-mataltelo*,
I don't know if that's about twenty lines down, beginning of a
line, he says in the narrow lines, he says, כגון זה שמי
שהתיר קשר העליון *kegon zeh she-mi she-hitir kesher ha-elyon* from the when
you undo the top, אם אתה מטלטלו *im atah metaltelo*, if you
were to try to carry it, הוא ניתק מאליו *hu nitak me-elav*,
the whole thing would anyway fall apart. שאין לו אלא פיו קלוע
כמו גדיל לאחוז את הנצרים *she-ein lo ela piv kalua ke-mo gdila
le-echoz et ha-natzarim*, you only have this like woven thing. So for
רש"י *Rashi*, it sounds like a little different. Like רש"י *Rashi*, if
you wanted to read רש"י *Rashi* in a very minimalist way, he
would be saying the reason it's not considered a bundle is because
it won't stay together. And that that's not the purpose of the
bottom weave. So if you take something like a mat, you'll say
but a mat does stay together, so maybe it is called a
bundle because it all does stay together. But nevertheless we're going to
see a later גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that's going to be clear that
mats that are not מקבל טומאה tumah *mekabel tumah*, even though they're
woven, are not considered to be bundles, are considered okay. So it
does seem that the basic idea here is, look, even with the
weave, it's not a normal bundle, which is separate discrete units brought
together in some outer string holding them together. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמר רבי אבא Rabbi Abba אמר
שמואל *Amar Rabbi Abba amar Shmuel*: ירקות שאמרו חכמים אדם יוצא בהן
ידי חובתו בפסח *Yerakos she-amru chachamim adam yotzei bahen yedei chovato ba-Pesach*.
So it seems like we're not getting away from the מרור *maror*.
Like it is fascinating sometimes the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* keeps
on doubling back in things that don't seem so relevant. Like first
we talked about אזוב *ezov* which with a we talked about מרור
*maror* with an attendant name like swamp מרור *maror* and אזוב *ezov*
with an attendant name. And that seemed to be like a total
digression, right, because it was the same person who said one thing
mentioned a string about מרור *maror*. But we brought in the discussion
of מרור *maror* and אזוב *ezov*. And now we're not giving up
on them. We then discussed אזוב *ezov* in terms of defining the
minimum bundle, and now we're going to discuss מרור *maror* and the
use of מרור *maror* for סכך skach *schach* in your סוכה sukkah
*sukkah*. So it's quite fascinating how we're like doubling back on these
things which seem to be a digression. So let's take a
look. ירקות שאמרו חכמים אדם יוצא בהן ידי חובתו בפסח *Yerakos she-amru
chachamim adam yotzei bahen yedei chovato ba-Pesach*, מביאין את הטומאה *mevi'in et
ha-tumah*, number they transfer טומאה tumah. *tumah*, ואין חוצצין בפני הטומאה *ve-ein
chotzin bifnei ha-tumah*. What does that mean? It means, right, if you
have here something that's a roof, right, an אהל *ohel*, right, it's
a טפח *tefach* by a טפח *tefach* off the ground and you
have a מת *meis* down here, right, so the הלכה halacha: *halacha*
is, you have a corpse underneath it, the טומאה tumah *tumah* if
it's a טפח *tefach* above, the טומאה tumah *tumah* hits and it
spreads underneath the roof, but it doesn't go above. So this is
מביא *mevin*, it spreads the טומאה tumah *tumah* to everything underneath it,
but it's חוצץ *chotzetz*,
it's a block, it's an obstacle for the טומאה tumah *tumah* to
proceed above. Okay, now normally those things go together. If something is
מביא את הטומאה *mevia et ha-tumah*, it's also חוצץ *chotzetz*. If you
didn't have a roof, it wouldn't be מביא *mevi*, it wouldn't go
across, but it would be אינו חוצץ *eino chotzetz*, it would go
through. Some types of things from a rabbinic perspective or whatever, sometimes
it could be biblical, but first we'll say rabbinic, has the worst
of both worlds. It both spreads the טומאה tumah *tumah* underneath it
and it allows טומאה tumah *tumah* to go above it. And one
example would be these types of vegetables from מרור *maror*. If you
use them as your roof, they were above your טומאה tumah *tumah*,
your dead body, it would be מביא *mevi*, it would bring it
because it's a physical object, it's wide enough, but the טומאה tumah
*tumah* would also continue above. Why? And what we're going to see
is, is because these are types of things, like we discussed before
certain things, leaves or whatever, which will wither and crumble, these are
types of things that when they would dry out will crumble and
therefore after a while there won't be a roof over the top.
And the rabbis were afraid you won't be paying attention. So therefore
they had to say, it's like it's already crumbled, and you have
the worst of both worlds. Since it now is present, it brings
the טומאה tumah, *tumah*, since it eventually will be crumbled, we look
at it as if that's already happened and the טומאה tumah. *tumah*
goes through it. Okay, so that's for laws of טומאה *tumah*, but
now we're going to see how that's relevant for סוכה sukkah. *sukkah*.
ופוסלין בסוכה משום אויר *U-poslin ba-sukkah mi-shum avir* and also it invalidates
the סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* משום אויר *mi-shum avir* like air. מאי טעמא
mai taama? *Mai ta'ama*? Now what would you say before that little
word of air? Could you use this for סכך skach. *schach*? Could
you use מרור *maror* for סכך skach *schach*? It's food.
It couldn't be food.
Like it's מקבל טומאה *mekabel tumah*, so you can't use it. But
if it's just bad סכך skach *schach* and bad סכך skach *schach*,
what's the הלכה *halacha* bad סכך skach *schach*? So we're going to
find out that bad סכך skach *schach* invalidates only if it's four
טפחים tfachim *tefachim*. Less than four טפחים tfachim? *tefachim* is not a
problem. There's also another big leniency of bad סכך skach. *schach* if
you'll remember the principle of the bending wall, right? So the principle
of the bending wall is here's your סוכה sukkah, *sukkah*, right, if
you have bad סכך skach, *schach* here up to four אמות amos
*amos*, right, you can envision this as a bent wall. So bad
סכך sechach, *schach* is not the end of your סוכה sukkah *sukkah*.
If it's juxtaposed, contiguous to the wall, it actually can be up
to four אמות *amos* and your סוכה sukkah *sukkah* could still be
good. Even if the bad סכך sechach, *schach* were in the middle,
it would only be a problem of four טפחים tfachim *tefachim*. So
that's by bad סכך sechach. *schach*. However, if it's air, if you
have no סכך sechach, *schach*, then once it is three טפחים tfachim
*tefachim* of air, once this is three טפחים tfachim *tefachim* of air,
okay, it's no good. Why? Because once it's three טפחים tfachim you
can't say לבוד lavud and then your סכך sechach, isn't attached to
your walls. So air is a bigger problem than bad סכך. sechach,
Okay? Okay,
and if it's in the middle as well, once it's three טפחים
tfachim it's no good. Why? Because again, then the ceiling is not
connected. Like two separate ceilings, right?
Why couldn't you have a bent wall for the three טפחים?
Because walls are only physical. So even when we use the magic
of the bent wall, it needs the physical סכך sechach to view
it as a continuation of the wall, but if it's a break
of air, then it stops. There's no wall. The top... there's no
roof, right? So then you have no wall, the סכך sechach. isn't
connected to a wall, invalid. If there's three טפחים of air in
the middle, then you have סכך sechach. that are not connected, the
two parts of the סוכה sukkah, aren't connected to one another. Right,
that's assuming it's going the entire length of the סוכה. sukkah, If
this was an aerial view, right, you were looking from above and
that was your סוכה, sukkah that was your three טפחים of air,
right, so you don't have a כשר kosher סוכה, sukkah right? This
has, you know, I mean well maybe you have a כשר kosher
but only half of your סוכה sukkah? is כשר. kosher. I mean
depending on if you have let's say three walls here or something
like that. This divides your סוכה down in half so they can't...
you can't have a split. I thought the rule for סכך sechach
was just you have to have more shade than sun, why not?
Well, but you have to have a continuous roof. If you have,
yeah, that's... we'll discuss more of that later. But yes, if it's...
so if there's a... if there's a whole split three טפחים down,
then the סכך sechach is not connected to itself, okay? So anyway,
so it's worse for something to be air than for it to
be... what do you call... for it to be פסול סכך. pasul
skach. Actually, you know, if you've got a big thing of air
in your סוכה, you're better off putting פסול סכך pasul skach to
fill it up than to leave it as air. If you have
a big thing of air in your סוכה, you're better off filling
it with פסול סכך pasul skach than leaving it as air. So
the חידוש chiddush here is, you've got this horseradish as your סכך.
s'chach, Technically אביי Abaye should say you're going to leave your סוכה
because it'll be smelly, that's what אביי Abaye is thinking. But anyway,
technically it's פסול סכך pasul skach and okay, if it's less than
four טפחים you're fine or even less than four אמות if it's
against the edge of the wall. But comes along the גמרא Gemara
and says no, actually, once it's three טפחים it's invalid. It's like
it's air, it's as bad as air. Why is it as bad
as air? So like what they say on the radio, right? The
worst thing is dead air, right? So fill it up with anything,
it's better than dead air. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay? So ופוסל בסוכה משום
אוויר, uposel basukkah mishum avir, it's invalid like a סוכה like air,
not just like פסול סכך. pasul skach. מאי טעמא? Why is this
true? Both questions, why does it not be a barrier for טומאה
and why is it as bad as air for the סוכה? דכיון
דכי יבשי פרחי ונפלי, dikivan dechi yavshi parchi venafli, since once it
dries out it crumbles and falls down, כמאן דליתנהו דמי, keman deleitnehu
dami, you look at it even now as though that happened because
we're afraid you won't be paying attention and therefore we treat it
now as the worst case scenario in the end and therefore it's
like it's air so it doesn't stop טומאה.
Will it immediately be a physical gap?
Once it dries out, yes, it will crumble
and fall down.
Metaphorically or like it just...
I don't know, and I don't know why the גמרא says all
the vegetables of מרירא, merira, are they all the same and they're
different that way than other foods? Other foods don't crumble, so I
don't know, but
interesting it's the same reason. Really in the real world the vegetables
of מרירא merira
don't do that same thing with טומאה where they have טומאה underneath
and טומאה above. The רבנים rabbanim sort of made it because they
might crumble. Same thing here.
Exactly. It's the same explanation for טומאה as it is by... as
it is by the סכך, s'chach why it's treated as
air. So כמאן דליתנהו דמי, keman deleitnehu dami, even now we view
it as though they're no longer there. Fine. דאמר רבי אבא אמר
רב הונא, da'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav Huna, הבוצר
לגת אין לו ידות. habotzer lagat ein lo yadot. So now we
really start getting into the world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah vetaharah. If
you are harvesting
grapes, that's what the word בוצר botzer means, for the גת, gat,
for the pressing vat, I mean, to go to make it into
wine, אין לו ידות, ein lo yadot, the principle of a יד
yad hand does not apply. There's a basic principle of טומאה that
something that is attached to a vessel, let's say a vessel, you
have a handle on a jug, and you touch the טומאה to
the handle, the jug becomes טמא. tamei. It's like an extension of
the vessel. The same way that's true by a vessel, it's also
true by food. If you have an apple and you've got the
little like the twig that comes out of the apple, what's that
called, the twig? Stem? Thank you, you have the stem. So since
that's used as a handle so sometimes you'll pick up the apple
by the stem, right? So then, or let's say by your grape,
you know you've got the whole stalk or whatever it is and
you pick it up by that stalk, so that serves as a
handle to the grape. So even though the stalk by itself doesn't
become טמא, tamei, if it's attached to the grape and you touch
טומאה to the stalk, the grape becomes טמא tamei or the apple
becomes טמא. tamei. That's called a יד, yad, a handle.
Why does the stalk not become טמא?
tamei? Because it's not food, it's just a piece of wood, right,
if it were by itself, right? But if it's serving as a
handle to the food, it transfers טומאה to the food. So now,
let's say you're harvesting grapes to make wine. So in that case,
you don't want those stems, right? If you're eating grapes, you maybe
want those stems as a way of holding onto the grape. But
if you're harvesting it for wine, you don't want those stems, they're
just getting in the way. So even though physically they're attached, they're
not considered
a יד, yad, a
handle. And for making wine, then the idea of יד yad doesn't
apply and those stems do not communicate טומאה, do not transfer טומאה.
So that's what he says: רב מנשיא בר גדא Rav Menashia bar
Gadda אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, הקוצץ לסכך אין לו ידות.
Hakotzetz le-sechach ein lo yadot.
Let's say you are harvesting
grapes and you want to use the grapes and the vine for
סכך, s'chach, then the idea of יד yad does not apply. Now,
it's a little bit funny because you don't actually want the grapes
for the סכך, s'chach, you just want the vine for the סכך.
s'chach. But it's the same type of an idea. If you're harvesting
it for grapevine, let's say for סכך, s'chach you're not interested in
the grapes, so you don't want the grape attached to the stalk;
you just want the stalk. Okay, so conceptually it boils down to
the same thing: you don't want these two attached. Okay, so therefore
there as well. Now, that's relevant. Why is it relevant? Because if
you're putting your grapevine with the grapes up on your סכך, s'chach
you have to know how much of this is kosher סכך, how
much of it is פסול. pasul. Well, how about the part attached
to the grape? Does that get counted as part of the grape
for weighing the amount of פסול סכך, pasul sechach, or does it
get counted as part of the rest of the
vine?
Okay, and he says—are you allowed to
actually—yeah, well there could be a certain amount of פסול סכך pasul
sechach as long as it's mixed up and it's in the minority.
Wait, but are you worried you're going to like start plucking the
grapes on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
Alright, that's a different issue about מוקצה למצוותו, muktzah le-mitzvaso, where we
say where we're not worried; you can put up stuff also for
like decoration. So let's take a look. The גמרא says like this:
okay, הקוצץ לסכך אין לו ידות. Hakotzetz le-sechach ein lo yadot. מאן
דאמר קוצץ, man d'amar kotzetz, if you say the case of—by the
way, right, קוצץ kotzetz might not also be referring to things other
than grapes; you could be cutting down, I don't know, big fronds
of palm trees and have some bananas attached to it, okay. So
the one that says that the case by סכך it's not a
יד, yad, כל שכן בוצר, kol she-kein botzer, you would certainly say
by the case of harvesting grapes that the twigs are—that the twigs
are not a יד. yad. דלא ניחא ליה, de-la nicha leh, because
you obviously don't want it connected to the grape. דלא נמציי ליה
חמרא, de-la nimtzei leh chamra, because it's going to absorb—if you have
stalks in your vat, it's going to, you know, suck up the
wine. It'll absorb the wine, and you don't want that; it'll also—it'll
impurify the wine. So there's no question that you don't want the
stalks when you're making wine and that it's not considered a יד.
yad. But מאן דאמר בוצר, man d'amar botzer, but if you just
gave your example by the harvesting grapes that it's not a יד,
yad, שאין לו ידות, she-ein lo yadot, you might not agree to
the case of סכך. אבל קוצץ יש לו ידות, aval kotzetz yesh
lo yadot, by—by
cutting off like palms of—you know, branches of a tree, you might
have a principle of יד. yad. Why? You don't want it connected
to the food, so why are they considered to be like a
unit? דניחא ליה דליסמך בהו, de-nicha leh de-lismach behu, because you do
want it connected to the pieces of fruit that's on the—on the
branch. Why? כי היכי דלא לבדרו, ki heichi de-la livdru, so it
shouldn't scatter. Meaning, you know, if you have a—you might want the
nice heavy piece of fruit attached because it'll weigh down the branch
and it'll keep the branch in place. So even though it's פסול
סכך, pasul sechach, you might want it to be attached to the—to
the branch because the heavy fruit will keep the branch in place.
And since you want it attached, the idea of יד yad would
still apply because there's a desire to attach the fruit with the
stalk that is—that is connected to it. Okay, so there you could
actually say that it is considered part of the fruit because you
want the fruit connected to the branch and therefore it counts as
פסול סכך. pasul sechach. So now the גמרא just tries to prove
this: לימא דרב מנשיא בר גדא תנאי היא, leima de-Rav Menashia bar
Gadda tanna'ei hi, let's say this issue is a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. דתניא, de-tanya, taught in a ברייתא: Baraisa: סוכי תאנים ובהם תאנים,
sochei te'einim u-vahem te'einim, branches of a figs—fig branches and with figs
attached to them; פרכילין ובהן ענבים, parchilin u-vahen anavim, or clusters of
grapes—I'm sorry—yeah, like whatever, like grapevines, whatever, clusters with the grapes still
on them; קשין ובהן שבולין, kashin u-vahen shibbolin, or—or straws with the—ears
still attached to it; וחבטות ובהן תמרים, ve-chavatot u-vahen temarim, or big
fronds of palm trees with the—dates still attached to it; כולן, kullan,
and you use these for סכך. So the wood part, the branch
part and the leaves are kosher; the fruit part is פסול. pasul.
So here's the הלכה: אם פסולת מרובה על האוכלים, im psolet merubbah
al ha-ochalim, if the waste product, meaning the, you know, the leaves
and the branches is more than the food—than the food part, כשרה,
kesherah, it's kosher because again, remember this idea that if you have
a mixture of סכך kosher and פסול סכך, pasul sechach, you can
go by the majority. ואם לאו פסולה, ve-im lav psulah, and if
not, it's invalid. Okay, you go by—you figure out what the majority
is. By the way, you have to love the irony that the
name for kosher סכך is פסולת, psolet, which is like פסול. pasul.
And that's from the similar דרשה drashah of פסולת גורן ויקב, psolet
goren ve-yekev, the remnant of what comes from the threshing floor. אחרים
אומרים, acherim omerim, others say: עד שיהא קש מרובה על הידות ועל
האוכלים. ad she-ye'hei kash merubbeh al ha-yadot ve-al ha-ochalim. No, it's not
enough to have more of the other stuff than the fruit—than the
fruit; it has to be more than the fruit and the twigs
that are attached to the fruit. That gets counted in the פסול
סכך. pasul sechach. So you see, this seems to be what's being
debated. Do you count the twigs in the פסול סכך psul s'chach
as part of the fruit or not? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai
lav beha kamiflagi? This is the debate. This seems to be the
debate: דמר סבר יש להן ידות demar savar yesh lahen yadot that
there are hands, that the twigs are part of the fruit when
cut for סכך, ומר סבר אין להן ידות umar savar ein lahen
yadot that it's not, that seems to be exactly the issue. לרבי
אבא בריתא תנאי le'Rabbi Abba bareita tana'ei for רבי אבא who says
even when you cut it for
סכך they are they're considered to be hands, that's certainly a debate
of תנאים Tana'im because here you see there are some that say
they're not hands. לרבי מנשה בר גדא מי איכא תנאי le'Rabbi Menashe
bar Gadda mi ika tana'ei but for רבי מנשה בר גדא Rabbi
Menashe bar Gadda is it a debate of תנאים? Tana'im? No. אמר
לך רבי מנשה amar lach Rabbi Menashe דכולי עלמא סבירא dechulei alma
sevira הקוצצו לסיכוך אין לו ידות. hakotzo lesichuch ein lo yadot. I'll
say no, when you're doing it for the סכך, for the purpose
of סכך, everybody agrees you don't want the fruit connected and they're
considered separate and there's no concept of hands. So why is there
a concept of hands in this case? דהכא במאי עסקינן dehacha bemai
askinan כגון שקצצן לאכילה ונמלך עליהן לסיכוך. kegon shekotzan leachilah venimlach aleihen
lesichuch.
The case here where there is a debate whether the whether the
twigs are considered part of the fruit or not is not when
you cut it for סכך. If you cut it for סכך you
don't want it attached and it's not considered part of the fruit.
The debate here where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it is part
of the fruit and it's invalid was when initially it was cut
for the purpose of fruit, and if it's initially it was cut
for the purpose of fruit, okay,
then it is considered part of the fruit. So we'll pick up
with this tomorrow because that was a little bit rushed, but the
basic idea is is that there is an opinion that says it's
part of the fruit, but the claim is that would not be
the normal case, normal if it's for סכך it's separate, it's only
part of the fruit when you were cutting it for the sake
of fruit, then you do have the concept of יד. yad. Alright
to be continued tomorrow.
גמרא סוכה דף טז, Gemara Sukkah Daf Tet-Zayin, about in the middle
of the page.